So last year, on the Fourth of July,
اذا العام الماضي, في الرابع من يوليو(تموز)
experiments at the Large Hadron Collider
التجارب في مسارع الجسيمات الضخم
discovered the Higgs boson.
كشفت عن جسيم هيقز بوزونز
It was a historical day.
لقد كان يوما تاريخيا.
There's no doubt that from now on,
لايوجد شك انه من الان فصاعدا,
the Fourth of July will be remembered
الرابع من يوليو(تموز) سيتم نذكره
not as the day of the Declaration of Independence,
ليس فقط انه يوم اعلان الاستقلال الامريكي,
but as the day of the discovery of the Higgs boson.
ولكن يوم اكتشاف جسيم هيقز بوزون.
Well, at least, here at CERN.
حسنا, على الاقل, هنا في سيرن.
But for me, the biggest surprise of that day
ولكن بالنسبة لي, اكبر مفاجأة في اليوم
was that there was no big surprise.
انه لم تكن هناك أي مفاجأة.
In the eye of a theoretical physicist,
في نظر علماء الفيزياء النظرية,
the Higgs boson is a clever explanation
جسيم هبقز بوزون هو طريقة شرح ذكية
of how some elementary particles gain mass,
للكيفية التي تكتسب بها الجسيمات الاولية كتلة,
but it seems a fairly unsatisfactory
و لكن ذلك يبدو غير مقبول الى حد ما
and incomplete solution.
و حل غير مكتمل.
Too many questions are left unanswered.
الكثير من الاسئلة تركت دون اجابات.
The Higgs boson does not share the beauty,
لا يتشارك جسيم هيقز بوزون في الجمال,
the symmetry, the elegance,
أو التناظر, أو الاناقة,
of the rest of the elementary particle world.
مع عالم الجسيمات الاولية الاخرى.
For this reason, the majority of theoretical physicists
و لهذا السبب, معظم علماء الفيزياء النظرية
believe that the Higgs boson could not
يعتقدون أن جسيم هيقز بوزون لا يمكن
be the full story.
أن يكون هو القصة الكاملة.
We were expecting new particles and new phenomena
نحن نتوقع جسيمات جديدة و ظواهر جديدة
accompanying the Higgs boson.
مصاحبة لجسيم هيقز بوزون.
Instead, so far, the measurements
عزضا عن ذلك, حتى الان, القياسات
coming from the LHC show no signs of new particles
القادمة من مسارع الجسيمات الضخم لا تظهر أي علامات لعنصر جديد
or unexpected phenomena.
أو ظاهرة غير متوقعة.
Of course, the verdict is not definitive.
بالطبع, الحكم غبر نهائي.
In 2015, the LHC will almost double
في عام 2015, مسارع الجسيمات الضخم سيقوم تقريبا بمضاعفة
the energy of the colliding protons,
طاقة الجسيمات المتصادمة,
and these more powerful collisions
و هذه الاصطدامات ذات القوة الاعلى
will allow us to explore further the particle world,
ستسمح لنا بالغوص أكثر في عالم الجسيمات,
and we will certainly learn much more.
و بالتاكيد سنتعلم أكثر بكثير.
But for the moment, since we have found
و لكن في الوقت الحالي, و بما أننا لم نجد
no evidence for new phenomena, let us suppose
أي دليل على ظاهرة جديدة, سنفترض
that the particles that we know today,
أن الجسيمات التي نعرفها في وقتنا الحالي,
including the Higgs boson,
متضمنة جسيم هيقز بوزون,
are the only elementary particles in nature,
هي الجسيمات الاولية الوحيدة في الطبيعة,
even at energies much larger
حتى في طاقات أعلى بكثير
than what we have explored so far.
من التي قد استكشفناها حتى الان.
Let's see where this hypothesis is going to lead us.
لننظر أين ستقودنا هذه الفرضية.
We will find a surprising and intriguing result
سوف نجد نتيجة مفاجاة و مثيرة للفضول
about our universe, and to explain my point,
عن كوننا, و حتى أشرح قصدي,
let me first tell you what the Higgs is about,
دعوني أخبركم عن ماذا يتحدث هيقز,
and to do so, we have to go back
و حتى افعل ذلك, لابد من العودة
to one tenth of a billionth of a second
الى العشر من الجزء من المليار من الثانية
after the Big Bang.
قبل الانفجار الكبير.
And according to the Higgs theory,
و على حسب نظرية هيقز,
at that instant, a dramatic event took place
في تلك اللحظة, حصل حدث دراماتيكي
in the universe.
في الكون.
Space-time underwent a phase transition.
خضع بعد الزمكان الى تغيير في الطور.
It was something very similar to the phase transition
لقد كان شيئا شبيها جدا بالتغيير في الطور
that occurs when water turns into ice
الذي يحدث عندما يتحول الماء الى ثلج
below zero degrees.
تحت درجة الصفر المئوية.
But in our case, the phase transition
و لكن في حالتنا هذه, التغيير في الطور
is not a change in the way the molecules
ليس تغيير في ترتيب الجزيئات
are arranged inside the material,
داخل المادة,
but is about a change
ولكن تغيير
of the very fabric of space-time.
في النسيج الاساسي لبعد الزمكان.
During this phase transition, empty space
خلال فترة التغيير في الطور, الفراغ الخالي
became filled with a substance
اصبح مليئا بالمواد
that we now call Higgs field.
و التي نسميها الان مجال هيقز.
And this substance may seem invisible to us,
و هذه المادة قد تكون غير مرئية بالنسبة لنا
but it has a physical reality.
و لكن لديها واقع فيزيائي.
It surrounds us all the time,
انها تحيط بنا في جميع الاوقات,
just like the air we breathe in this room.
تمام مثل الهواء الذي نتنفسه في هذه الغرفة.
And some elementary particles interact
و بعض الجزيمات الاولية تتفاعل
with this substance, gaining energy in the process.
مع هذه المادة, و تكتسب طاقة أثناء هذه العملية.
And this intrinsic energy is what we call
و هذه الطاقة الجوهرية هي ما نسميه
the mass of a particle,
كتلة الجسيم,
and by discovering the Higgs boson, the LHC
و باكتشاف جسيم هبقز بوزون, مسارع الجسيمات الضخم
has conclusively proved that this substance is real,
أثبت بشكل قاطع أن هذه المادة حقيقية,
because it is the stuff the Higgs bosons are made of.
لانها هي المادة التي يتكون منها جسيم هيقز بوزون
And this, in a nutshell, is the essence of the Higgs story.
وذلك باختصار, هو ماهية قصة هيقز.
But this story is far more interesting than that.
ولكن هذه القصة حتى أكثر اثارة للاهتمام من ذلك
By studying the Higgs theory,
عند دراسة نظرية هيقز,
theoretical physicists discovered,
اكتشف علماء الفيزياء النظرية,
not through an experiment
ليس عن طريق التجربة
but with the power of mathematics,
ولكن باستخدام قوة الرياضيات,
that the Higgs field does not necessarily exist
أنه ليس بالضرورة أن يكون مجال هيقز موجودا
only in the form that we observe today.
فقط بالطريقة التي نشاهدها اليوم.
Just like matter can exist as liquid or solid,
تمام مثلما تتواجد المادة كسائل أو صلب,
so the Higgs field, the substance that fills all space-time,
اذا مجال هيقز, المادة التي تملأ كل الزمكان
could exist in two states.
يمكن أن تتواجد في حالتين.
Besides the known Higgs state,
بالاضافة الحالة المعروفة لهيقز,
there could be a second state in which the Higgs field
يمكن أن يكون هناك حالة أخرى يكون فيها مجال هيقز
is billions and billions times denser
أكثر كثافة بملايين الملايين من المرات
than what we observe today,
مما نشاهده اليوم,
and the mere existence of another state
و مجرد وجود حالة أخرى
of the Higgs field poses a potential problem.
من مجال هيقز يشكل مشكلة محتملة.
This is because, according to the laws
و سبب ذلك, على حسب قوانين
of quantum mechanics, it is possible
ميكانيكا الكم, من الممكن
to have transitions between two states,
أن بحدث انتقال بين الحالتين,
even in the presence of an energy barrier
حتى في وجود حاجز للطاقة
separating the two states,
يفصل بين الحالتين,
and the phenomenon is called,
و هذه الظاهرة تسمى,
quite appropriately, quantum tunneling.
بشكل مناسب تماما, نفق الكم.
Because of quantum tunneling,
بسبب نفق الكم,
I could disappear from this room
من الممكن أن اختفي من هذه الغرفة
and reappear in the next room,
و أظهر في الغرفة التالية,
practically penetrating the wall.
عمليا, مخترقا الجدار.
But don't expect me to actually perform the trick
و لكن لا تتوقعوا مني أن اقوم بالخدعة
in front of your eyes, because the probability
أمام اعينكم, لان احتمال
for me to penetrate the wall is ridiculously small.
أن اخترق الجدار صغير لدرجة تبعث على السخرية.
You would have to wait a really long time
سيكون عليكم أن تنتظروا لمدة طويلة جدا
before it happens, but believe me,
قبل أن يحدث ذلك, ولكن صدقوني,
quantum tunneling is a real phenomenon,
نفق الكم ظاهرة حقيقية,
and it has been observed in many systems.
و تمت مشاهدتها في العديد من الانظمة.
For instance, the tunnel diode,
على سبيل المثال, الثنائي النفقي,
a component used in electronics,
وهو مكون يستخدم في الالكترونيات,
works thanks to the wonders
يعمل بفضل عجائب
of quantum tunneling.
نفق الكم.
But let's go back to the Higgs field.
ولكن لنعود الى مجال هيقز.
If the ultra-dense Higgs state existed,
اذا وجدت حالة هيقز فائقة الكثافة,
then, because of quantum tunneling,
اذا, و بسبب نفق الكم,
a bubble of this state could suddenly appear
قد تظهر فقاعة من هذه الحالة فجأة
in a certain place of the universe at a certain time,
في مكان و زمان معينين في الكون,
and it is analogous to what happens when you boil water.
و هي مماثلة لما يحدث عند غليان الماء.
Bubbles of vapor form inside the water,
تتشكل فقاعات من البخار داخل الماء,
then they expand, turning liquid into gas.
و من ثم تتمدد, محولة السائل الى غاز.
In the same way, a bubble of the ultra-dense Higgs state
و بنفس الطريقة, فقاعة من حالة هيقز فائقة الكثافة
could come into existence because of quantum tunneling.
قد تتواجد بسبب نفق الكم.
The bubble would then expand at the speed of light,
بعد ذلك ستتمدد الفقاعة بسرعة الضوء,
invading all space, and turning the Higgs field
محتلة الفضاء كله, و محولة مجال هيقز
from the familiar state into a new state.
من الحالة المعروفة الى الحالة الجديدة.
Is this a problem? Yes, it's a big a problem.
هل هذه مشكلة؟ أجل, انها مشكلة كبيرة.
We may not realize it in ordinary life,
قد لا ندركها في الحياة العادية,
but the intensity of the Higgs field is critical
و لكن كثافة مجال هيقز امر بالغ الاهمية
for the structure of matter.
لبنية المادة.
If the Higgs field were only a few times more intense,
اذا كان مجال هيقز اكثر شدة بعدة مرات,
we would see atoms shrinking, neutrons decaying
كنا سنرى الذرات تنكمش, و النيوترونات تتحلل
inside atomic nuclei, nuclei disintegrating,
داخل الانوية الذرية, و الانوية تتفكك,
and hydrogen would be
و الهيدروجين سيصبح
the only possible chemical element in the universe.
العنصر الكيميائي الوحيد الممكن في الكون.
And the Higgs field, in the ultra-dense Higgs state,
و مجال هيقز, في حالة هيقز فائقة الكثافة,
is not just a few times more intense than today,
ليس فقط عدة مرات أكثر شدة عن اليوم,
but billions of times,
بي مليارات المرات,
and if space-time were filled by this Higgs state,
واذا كان الزمكان مليئا بحالة هيقز هذه,
all atomic matter would collapse.
كل المواد الذرية سوف تنهار.
No molecular structures would be possible, no life.
لن تكون هنال بنية ذرية ممكنة, لا حياة.
So, I wonder, is it possible
اذا, أتسائل, هل من الممكن
that in the future, the Higgs field
في المستقبل, أن يخضع مجال هيقز
will undergo a phase transition and,
الى تغيير في الطور,
through quantum tunneling, will be transformed
و عبر نفق الكم, أن يتحول
into this nasty, ultra-dense state?
الى هذه الحالة البغيضة فائقة الكثافة؟
In other words, I ask myself, what is the fate
أو في عبارة اخرى, سألت نفسي, ما هو مصير
of the Higgs field in our universe?
مجال هيقز في كوننا؟
And the crucial ingredient necessary
و العنصر الحاسم اللازم
to answer this question is the Higgs boson mass.
للاجابة على هذا السؤال هو كتلة جسيم هيقز بوزون.
And experiments at the LHC found that the mass
تجربة في مسارع الجسيمات الضخم وجدت ان كتلة
of the Higgs boson is about 126 GeV.
جسيم هيقز بوزون هي حوال 126GeV.
This is tiny when expressed in familiar units,
وهذه الوحدة صغيرة عند التعبير عنها بالوحدات المألوفة,
because it's equal to something like
لانها شيئا مثل
10 to the minus 22 grams,
10 مرفوعة الى القوة سالب 22 جرام,
but it is large in particle physics units,
ولكنها كبيرة في وحدات الفيزياء الجزيئية,
because it is equal to the weight
لانها تساوي وزن
of an entire molecule
جزيء كامل
of a DNA constituent.
من تأسيسية الحمض النووي (DNA).
So armed with this information from the LHC,
اذا مسلحين بالمعلومات من مسارع الجسيمات الضخم,
together with some colleagues here at CERN,
انا و زميل لي هنا في سيرن,
we computed the probability
حسبنا احتمالية
that our universe could quantum tunnel
أن يحدث نفق الكم في كوننا
into the ultra-dense Higgs state,
الى حالة هيقز فائقة الكثافة,
and we found a very intriguing result.
و وجدنا نتيجة مثيرة للفضول.
Our calculations showed
أظهرت حساباتنا
that the measured value of the Higgs boson mass
أن القمة المقاسة لكتلة جسيم هيقز بوزون
is very special.
خاصة جدا.
It has just the right value
انها القيمة الصحيحة
to keep the universe hanging
حتى تحافظ على الكون
in an unstable situation.
في حالة مستقرة.
The Higgs field is in a wobbly configuration
مجال هيقز في حالة متهادية
that has lasted so far
و هذه الحالة قد ظلت هكذا حتى الان
but that will eventually collapse.
و لكن في نهاية الامر ستنهار.
So according to these calculations,
اذا و على حسب هذه الحسابات,
we are like campers
نحن مثل المعسكرين
who accidentally set their tent
الذين و عن طريق الخطأ نصبوا خيمتهم
at the edge of a cliff.
على حافة هاوية.
And eventually, the Higgs field
و في نهاية المطاف, مجال هيقز
will undergo a phase transition
سوف يخضع الى تغيير في الطور
and matter will collapse into itself.
و ستنهار المادة على نفسها.
So is this how humanity is going to disappear?
اذا هل هذه هي الطريقة التي ستختفي بها البشرية؟
I don't think so.
لا أعتقد ذلك.
Our calculation shows that quantum tunneling
حساباتنا توضح أن نفق الكم
of the Higgs field is not likely to occur
لمجال هيقز ليس من المحتمل حدوثه
in the next 10 to the 100 years,
في ال10 مرفوعة الى القوة 100 سنة القادمة,
and this is a very long time.
و هذه فترة طويلة جدا.
It's even longer than
انها اطول حتى
the time it takes for Italy to form a stable government.
من الزمن الذي تحتاجه ايطاليا لتكون حكومة مستقرة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Even so, we will be long gone by then.
وحتى ان حدث ذلك, سنكون قد انقرضنا حتى ذلك الوقت.
In about five billion years,
في حوالي خمسة مليارات سنة,
our sun will become a red giant,
ستصبح شمسنا عملاقا أحمر اللون,
as large as the Earth's orbit,
بحجم مدار كوكب الارض,
and our Earth will be kaput,
و ستصبح أرضنا مفلسة,
and in a thousand billion years,
و في ألف ميار سنة,
if dark energy keeps on fueling
اذا استمرت الطاقة السداء بالتأجج
space expansion at the present rate,
توسع الفضاء بالمعدل الحالي,
you will not even be able to see as far as your toes,
لن تكون قادرا على الرؤية حتى أصابع قدميك,
because everything around you
لان كل شيء من حولك
expands at a rate faster than the speed of light.
توسع بمعدل اسرع من سرعة الضوء.
So it is really unlikely
اذا من غير المحتمل
that we will be around to see the Higgs field collapse.
ان نكون موجودين لنرى مجال هيقز ينهار.
But the reason why I am interested
و لكن السبب وراء اهتمامي
in the transition of the Higgs field
في تحول مجال هيقز
is because I want to address the question,
هو انني اريد ان اجيب على السؤال,
why is the Higgs boson mass so special?
لماذا كتلة جسيم هيقز بوزون خاصة؟
Why is it just right to keep the universe
لماذا هي بالكاد صحيحة للحفاظ على الكون
at the edge of a phase transition?
على حافة التغيير في الطور؟
Theoretical physicists always ask "why" questions.
علماء الفيزياء النظرية دائما يسألون "لماذا؟".
More than how a phenomenon works,
اكثر من كيفية عمل ظاهرة ما,
theoretical physicists are always interested in
علماء الفيزياء النظرية داثما مهتمون
why a phenomenon works in the way it works.
لماذا تعمل ظاهرة ما بالطريقة التي تعمل بها.
We think that this these "why" questions
نحن نعتقد أن أسئلة "لماذا؟" هذه
can give us clues
يمكن أن تعطينا أدلة
about the fundamental principles of nature.
عن المبادئ الاساسية للطبيعة.
And indeed, a possible answer to my question
و بالفعل, اجابة ممكنة لسؤالي
opens up new universes, literally.
تفتح أكوان جديدة, حرفيا.
It has been speculated that our universe
لقد تم التكهن من قبل أن كوننا
is only a bubble in a soapy multiverse
ليس الا فقاعة في أكوان صابونية متعددة
made out of a multitude of bubbles,
مصنوعة من عدد وفير من الفقاعات,
and each bubble is a different universe
و كل فقاعة هي عبارة عن كون مختلف
with different fundamental constants
له ثوابت اساسية مختلفة
and different physical laws.
و قوانين فيزيائية مختلفة.
And in this context, you can only talk about
و في هذا السياق, يمكنك الحديث فقط عن
the probability of finding a certain value of the Higgs mass.
احتمالية ايجاد قيمة محددة لكتلة جسيم فيقز بوزون.
Then the key to the mystery
اذا المفتاح لهذه المعضلة
could lie in the statistical properties
قد يكمن في الخصائص الاحصائية
of the multiverse.
لهذه الاكوان المتعددة.
It would be something like what happens
قد يكون شيئا مثل الذي يحدث
with sand dunes on a beach.
بالنسبة للكثبان الرملية على الشاطئ.
In principle, you could imagine to find sand dunes
مبدئيا, قد تتصور أن تجد كثبان رملية
of any slope angle in a beach,
باي ميلان على الشاطئ,
and yet, the slope angles of sand dunes
ومع ذلك, زوايا الميلان للكثبان الرملية
are typically around 30, 35 degrees.
عادة حوالي 30,35 درجة.
And the reason is simple:
و السبب بسيط:
because wind builds up the sand, gravity makes it fall.
لان الرياح تبني الكثبان و الجاذبية تجعلها تسقط.
As a result, the vast majority of sand dunes
كنتيجة لذلك, الغالبية العظمى من الكثبان الرملية
have slope angles around the critical value,
لها ميلان قريب من القيمة الحرجة,
near to collapse.
قريبة من الانهيار.
And something similar could happen
و شيء مماثل قد بيحدث
for the Higgs boson mass in the multiverse.
لكتلة جسيم هيقز بوزون في الاكوان المتعددة.
In the majority of bubble universes,
في الغالبية من الاكوان الفقاعية,
the Higgs mass could be around the critical value,
كتلة هيقز تكون قريبة من القيمة الحرجة,
near to a cosmic collapse of the Higgs field,
قريبة من انهيار كوني لمجال هيقز,
because of two competing effects,
بسبب مؤثرين متنافسين,
just as in the case of sand.
مثل ما هي الحالة مع الرمال.
My story does not have an end,
قصتي ليس لديها نهاية,
because we still don't know the end of the story.
لاننا لازلنا لا نعرف نهاية القصة.
This is science in progress,
ان هذا علم قيد التطوير,
and to solve the mystery, we need more data,
و لحل هذه المعضلة, نحتاج الى معطيات اكثر,
and hopefully, the LHC will soon add new clues
و على أمل أن يضيف مسرع الجسيمات الضخم المزيد من الادلة
to this story.
لهذه القصة.
Just one number, the Higgs boson mass,
رقم واحد فقط, كتلة جسيم هيقز بوزون,
and yet, out of this number we learn so much.
و مع ذلك, من هذا الرقم نتعلم الكثير.
I started from a hypothesis, that the known particles
بدأت بافتراض, أن الجسيمات المعروفة
are all there is in the universe,
هي كل موجودة في الكون,
even beyond the domain explored so far.
حتى ابعد من المجال الذي استكشفناه حتى الان.
From this, we discovered that the Higgs field
ومن ذلك, اكتشفنا ان مجال هيقز
that permeates space-time may be standing
الذي يتخلل الزمكان قد يكون
on a knife edge, ready for cosmic collapse,
على طرف سكين, مستعدا لانهيار كوني,
and we discovered that this may be a hint
و اكتشفنا ان ذلك قد يكون تلميحا
that our universe is only a grain of sand
أن كوننا ليس الا حبة رمل
in a giant beach, the multiverse.
على شاطئ ضخم, الاكوان المتعددة.
But I don't know if my hypothesis is right.
ولكن انا لا اعلم اذا كانت فرضيتي صحيحة.
That's how physics works: A single measurement
هكذا تعمل الفيزياء: قياس واحد
can put us on the road to a new understanding
قد يضعنا على الطرق الى فهم جديد
of the universe
للكون
or it can send us down a blind alley.
أو قد يرسلنا الى طريق مسدود.
But whichever it turns out to be,
ولكن في كلتا الحالتين,
there is one thing I'm sure of:
هنالك شيء واحد انا متأكد منه:
The journey will be full of surprises.
ستكون الرحلة مليئة بالمفاجآت.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)